Now, let's take a few simple examples of three different clients.
الآن لنأخذ بعض الأمثلة البسيطة لثلاثة عملاء مختلفين.
The first client here has a project proposal which is
العميل الأول لديه مشروع مقترح
not fully defined yet and is slowly unfolding over time.
لم يتم تحديده بشكل كامل بعد ويتكشف إطار العمل ببطء مع مرور الوقت.
The second has a well-defined goal for the project,
والعميل الثاني لديه مشروع مقترح محدد الأهداف
but the granular features are non-defined.
لكن التفاصيل الدقيقة غير محددة.
The third has the goal,
والمشروع الثالث له هدف
has the features well-defined,
وتفاصيله محددة
but there is a high chance that all the requirements will
ولكن هناك احتمالية كبيرة بأن جميع المتطلبات سوف
evolve and the features might get changed or new ones might get added.
تتطور والتفاصيل قد تتغير أو قد تُضاف تفاصيل ومتطلبات جديدة للمشروع.
In all of these three cases,
وفي جميع هذه الحالات الثلاث،
a fixed cost pricing structure is not really a good idea for
فإن العمل بنظام التكلفة الثابتة لن يكون فكرة جيدة
the simple reason that the scope is either not known fully or is likely to change,
لسبب بسيط وهو أن نطاق عمل المشروع غير واضح بشكل كامل ومن المرجح أن يتغير،
hence the time and material structure is better suited here.
ولذلك فإن العمل بنظام قياس الوقت والمجهود مناسب أكثر هنا.
The client only pays for the time that the developer spends
فالعميل يدفع فقط مقابل الوقت الذي يقضيه المطور
and is free to change the requirements as they evolve for the client.
ويستطيع العميل تغيير متطلباته عندما تدعو الحاجة لذلك.
If you remember our pricing framework slide,
إن كنت تتذكر شريحة عرض إطار التسعير،
where we introduced the two types of pricing frameworks,
عندما عرضنا نظامين للتسعير
it would be worth adding yet another point here;
يجب أن نُضيف لذلك نقطة أخرى هنا،
that the scope is well-defined in a fixed cost framework,
أن نطاق العمل بنظام الميزانية الثابتة يجب أن يكون محدد،
whereas it may not be as well-defined
بينما قد يكون نطاق العمل غير محدد
in a project with time and materials pricing structure.
في المشاريع التي تعمل بنظام قياس الوقت والمجهود.
Another important aspect of deciding a pricing structure at
ونقطة أخرى هامة يجب أن نذكرها مع اختيار نظام التسعير
the start of the project is that when you're discussing this with the client,
في بداية المشروع هي أنك عندما تتناقش مع العميل
they may not even know about the structures at all.
فقد تجده لا يعلم إطلاقًا أنظمة التسعير هذه.
You as a freelancer,
أنت كموظف حر،
need to subtly lay down the options before the client for them to choose from.
يجب أن تطرح جميع الخيارات أمام العميل ليختار بينهم.
The client would most likely be like,
سيقول العميل غالبًا
"I want to get a website built,
"أريد إنشاء موقع إلكتروني"
how much would it cost?"
"ما هي التكلفة؟"
You as a freelancer,
أنت كموظف حر،
need to walk them through the different pricing structures
يجب أن تُطلع العميل على خطط التسعير المختلفة
and also get a sense of what kind of website they need to get built.
وتعلم منه أيضًا أي نوع من المواقع يحتاج إليه.
While you're doing that, remember that focus on the maximizing the value of the client,
بينما تفعل ذلك، تذكر أن تركز على تعظيم قيمة العميل،
try to put yourself in the client's shoes and see what the client's priorities are,
ضع نفسك مكان العميل وحاول أن ترى أولوياته،
and try to align yourself with those priorities while deciding these pricing structures.
وحاول مواءمة نفسك مع تلك الأولويات أثناء تحديد هياكل التسعير هذه.